(781) 698-8032

phillip.soucy@gmail.com

www.phillipsoucy.info -

Greater Boston, MA

# PROFESSIONAL PROFILE

'Versatile, hands-on engineer fluent in material mechanics, with broad experiences contributing high-value solutions in fast-paced startup culture.'

With extensive high-demand experience and a Master's in Mechanics of Materials, I have a proven ability to join small teams with unique technical challenges and contribute meaningful technical results. Through design, practical hands-on skills, and analytical reasoning, I consistently deliver efficient and robust solutions.

#### **CORE SKILLS**

- Hands-on Competency
- Interpersonal Communication
- Technical Writing
- Project Management
- Test Design and Implementation
- CAD (Solidworks, NX)
- Engineering Design
- Basic Sensor Integration
- FEA (Abaqus/CAE)
- Practical Programming

# CAREER SUMMARY

## MKE Composites, Inc. / Desktop Metal

Senior Mechanical Engineer

*January 2019 – October 2019* 

#### Outline

Collaborated with a diverse, fast-paced team using scrum methodology to deliver a proof-of-concept carbon fiber "3D printer," resulting in company acquisition by partner, Desktop Metal.

### **Key Responsibilities and Achievements**

- Designed, prototyped, and integrated kinematic coupling mechanism for tool changing.
  New design utilized more affordable machined parts and more COTS components.
- Wrote custom G-code and system configuration files for machine control, tool changing macros, motion system characterization testing, and product demonstrations.
- Coordinated with vendors and technical experts to reduce critical lead and internal product/process development times.

## N12 Technologies, Inc.

Lead Mechanical Engineer, Ohio Operations

January 2018 – November 2018

#### **Outline**

Overseeing all mechanical and industrial design upgrades of N12's next-generation production CVD reactor, including related facility upgrades.

#### **Key Responsibilities and Achievements**

- Technical lead for industrial nanotube reactor projects surrounding stand-up of out-ofstate manufacturing facility, including retrofits and upgrades of facility and equipment.
- Worked with management to implement outsourced engineering operating model which enabled an effective increase in team capacity. Allowed company resources to focus on core competencies while keeping capital expenditure down during expansion.
- Managed the design, fabrication and installation of robot-loaded high-temperature conveying system, which enabled a 3x increase in capacity. Project budget of \$0.5M.
- Designed staffing, operational flow, and all support infrastructure for the conveyor.
- Oversaw all simulations performed for engineering team. Worked with external vendors to ensure on-time and on-budget delivery of realistic and reliable results.

#### Outline

Managed the maintenance and development program of N12's first production CVD reactor, leading to significant improvements in machine up-time, more stable base-state, and reductions in unplanned maintenance.

### **Key Responsibilities and Achievements**

- Spearheaded CVD reactor improvement program, resulting in 40-point improvement in production factor of OEE within 5-month period.
- Introduced "customer-focused" internal engineering model; solicited direct feedback from operators, resulting in significant improvement in operator quality-of-work.
- Designed, built, and supported custom laser micrometry equipment for quality control.
  Allowed production to move away from SEM imaging and reduced feedback time of quality metrics from weeks to minutes.
- Developed, implemented, and maintained CVD reactor maintenance log, which reduced downtime during planned maintenance and problem-solving efforts.

## **Massachusetts Materials Technologies LLC**

Co-Founder, Research Engineer, Safety Officer

March 2015 – April 2017

#### **Outline**

Specialized in intellectual property and lead fracture toughness research. Lead primary research and development operations for development and validation of Fracture Toughness Tester (FTT) proof-of-concept.

#### **Key Responsibilities and Achievements**

- Designed and fabricated proof-of-concept method and apparatus capable of minimallydestructive evaluation of ductile metal fracture toughness.
- Supported mechanical design team during production phases by proofing technical drawings, sourcing material, milling and turning parts, and assembling sub-assemblies.
- Drafted sections of, created illustrations for, and coordinated submission of 4 US utility patent applications (1 award), as well as several provisional applications.
- Developed and maintained on-site safety program, including Chemical Hygiene Plan.

## **Materials and Engineering Group LLC**

**Engineering Consultant** 

*October 2013 – April 2017* 

#### Outline

Working directly under the Principal Engineer, I performed and supported experiments and analyses for use in litigation of cases involving material failure.

#### **Key Responsibilities and Achievements**

- Developed and implemented evidence teardown procedures, including organizing inspection events hosting several engineering firms.
- Designed, fabricated, and operated test fixtures for exemplar samples to verify failure hypotheses and analytical findings. Recorded and organized results.
- Drafted memos and reports for clients on analytical and experimental results.

#### Keurig, Inc.

Brewer Engineering Co-op

*January 2013 – August 2013* 

Outline

Supported Brewer Engineering team on the design and testing of in-production and preproduction brewer systems. Primarily focused on test fixture design and implementation.

#### **Key Responsibilities and Achievements**

- Developed and implemented automated life-cycle testing apparatuses utilizing opensource electronics and programming.
- Diagnosed brewer failures and implemented prototype corrective components.
- Processed and analyzed data for internal engineering R&D qualification.
- Presented test program data to engineering and manufacturing teams in US and China.

#### **PATENTS**

#### **Awards**

U.S. Patent 9,897,523: "Contact mechanic tests using stylus alignment to probe material properties", February 20, 2018.

U.S. Patent 9,933,346: "Contact mechanic tests using stylus alignment to probe material properties", April 3, 2018.

### **Applications**

US20180275035A1: "Measurement of material properties under local tensile stress through contact mechanics", September 27, 2018.

# RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

## Northeastern Dept. of Mechanical and Industrial Engineering

Handgrip Force and Stylus Strain Relationship for Parkinson's Disease Assessment

#### **Outline**

Analytically reduced and modeled the grasping of a pen to determine a fundamental relationship between applied writing grip force and body strain. The resulting relationship enables medical researchers to develop devices which can simply and non-invasively collect handgrip information, which has been described as one of the best describing factors of the manifestation and progression of PD.

### **Key Responsibilities and Achievements**

- Reduced simplified loading geometry to represent a subject gripping a pen
- Derived analytical equations to represent force-strain relationship for simplified geometry
- Modified equation using results from series of Abaqus/CAE finite element simulations
- Verified equations against analytical and experimental results, to within 10% of solution

#### **EDUCATION**

# **Northeastern University**

Master of Science, Mechanical Engineering, Mechanics of Materials December 2017

Select Courses: Mechatronic Systems, Control Systems, Elasticity and Plasticity,

Materials Processing and Manufacturing

Honors: summa cum laude (GPA 3.87 / 4.00)

### Bachelor of Science, Mechanical Engineering

May 2016

**Select Courses:** Probability and Statistics, Microeconomics **Awards:** 2014 Janet P. Mackie Good Fellowship Award

Honors: magna cum laude (GPA 3.76 / 4.00), Member Pi Tau Sigma (Mechanical Engineering

Honor Society)

Activities: Club Wrestling, Club Cycling